Okay, בוקר טוב *boker tov*. We pick up today with the משנה
Mishnah *Mishna*, with today’s דף ע"ב *Daf Ayin Bet*, 72, but we’re
in the משנה mishna. *Mishna* in ע"א עמוד ב' *Ayin Aleph Amud
Bet*, and it’s going to be some very practical stuff coming up
today. And again, very interesting things in terms of the relationship, in
terms of the nature of the marriage, and what חז"ל Chazal *Chazal*
are sort of saying is or is not tenable. So the משנה
Mishna *Mishna* picks up on the following in ע"א עמוד ב' *Ayin
Aleph Amud Bet*. המדיר hamadir אשה Isha שלא תלך לבית אביה *Hamadir
isha shelo telech l'veit aviha*, a man takes a vow that prevents
his wife going to her father’s house. Now again, how does he
take that vow? What’s his power to take a vow? So again,
it must be one of these things where he says הנאת תשמישי
עליך *hana'at tashmishi alayich*, the benefit of sex with me is forbidden
to you, or actually no, that would be going against his obligation
to benefit. The pleasure of sex with you is forbidden to me
if you go to your father’s house. So it’s really the condition
rather than the vow, but the effect of it is that it
makes it impossible for her to go.
He doesn't want to see his in-laws, right?
Right. Or she shouldn't hear her in-laws. You’re always going back to
your father’s house and whatever.
Well, right, but it’s called father’s house because it’s a patriarchy. בזמן
שהוא עמה בעיר *Bizman shehu ima ba'ir*, if the father, if the
parent’s house is in the city and therefore there would be an
expectation for more regular visits, חודש אחד יקיים שנים יוציא yotzi. *chodesh
echad yakayem, shnayim yotzi*. So again, if it’s for one month, that’s
tolerable. More than that, he has to get a divorce. And again,
the question about whether this is the vow itself was explicitly said
don’t go for a month, or whether the vow is indefinite and
it’s how much time we give him to try to get out
of the vow.
That’s if they’re living in the city with the in-laws.
בזמן שהוא בעיר אחרת *Bizman shehu b'ir acheret*, and if the in-laws
live in a different city, but literally it’s the father lives in
a different city, רגל אחד regel echad. יקיים שלשה יוציא ויתן כתובה
yotzi v'yitein kesuva, *regel echad yakayem, shelosha yotzi v'yiten ktubah*, up to
one רגל *regel* is sustainable.
Three רגלים regalim *regalim*, he already, that’s not reasonable that she can’t
go to her father’s house three רגלים regalim. *regalim* in a row.
So of course the question is, what about two? Anyway, in that
case, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* will ask, he has to divorce her
and give her her כתובה kesubah *ktubah*. המדיר אשה Isha שלא תלך
לבית האבל *Hamadir isha shelo telech l'veit ha'evel*, now a person takes
a vow preventing his wife from going to the house of a
mourner. Again, it has to be some indirect vow, it has to
be a condition that would trigger a vow that would make sex
forbidden. המדיר אשה Isha שלא תלך לבית האבל או לבית המשתה *Hamadir
isha shelo telech l'veit ha'evel o l'veit hamishte*, or to a house
of rejoicing, but probably means a wedding. יוציא ויתן כתובה yotzi v'yitein
kesuva *yotzi v'yiten ktubah*, then again, that’s intolerable, he has to give
a כתובה kesubah *ktubah*, and doesn’t give any amount of time. I
guess because you never know when there’s going to be, I guess
you’d know when there’s going to be a wedding, but anyway you
never know when there’ll be a בית האבל *beit ha'evel*, so he
has to anyway go ahead and that’s considered immediately intolerable. יוציא ויתן
כתובה yotzi v'yiten kesuva. מפני שנועל בפניה *yotzi v'yiten ktubah mipney sheno'al
bifaneha*, you’re locking the door in her presence. You’re basically locking her
up in the house, you’re preventing her from a normal type of
social interactions which are a staple of somebody's communal life.
And we’ll see about that in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. I mean
it's not just you’re preventing pleasure, but you’re closing off certain important
social, communal interactions. What? Okay, right.
ואם היה טוען משום
דבר אחר רשאי
Ve-im hayah toen
mishum davar acher rashai, *V'im haya toen mishum davar acher rashay*, but
if he has another, if he has a legitimate reason why, and
we’ll see what that legitimate reason is in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*,
basically then that would be permissible, which is very interesting. So חז"ל
Chazal *Chazal* here are basically making a judgment whether it's not just
is life tolerable under these
situations because maybe if it weren't tolerable who cares what his reason
is, it's not tolerable. So it obviously is more of a weighing
about justified, a combination of sort of tolerable and justified.
Sometimes we have to make sacrifices for other things. Okay. על מנת
שתאמרי לפלוני מה שאמרת לי *Al menat shetomri l'ploni mah she'amart li*,
if he makes a vow that basically would be triggered unless she
tells somebody what she just said to him, או מה שאמרתי לך
*o mah she'amarti lach*, or something that I told you, you have
to go tell it to somebody else and if not then this
vow will be triggered. או שתהא ממלאה ומערה לאשפה O shetehei memaleh
u'mearah l'ashpah *O shetehei memala um'ara l'ashpah*, or that you should fill
things up and spill them into the garbage heap. יוציא yotzi ויתן
כתובה kesuva, *yotzi v'yiten ktubah*, he has to divorce and give her
כתובה kesuva. *ktubah*. So the first one we understand that it's not
so nice, but why is it so huge deal? And the last
thing about spilling into the garbage, we don't even understand at all
what it's talking about, why that's an issue. So let's take a
look at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
like this. הא גופא קשיא *Ha gufa kashya*, first of all, it's
an internal contradiction. אמרת רגל אחד יקיים *Amart regel echad yakayem*, if
you said for one רגל *regel* not going to the father's house
if it's in a different city, that you can, he can, that
you stay in the marriage, it's sustainable, but it means stay in
the marriage. הא שנים יוציא yotzi ויתן כתובה kesuva, *Ha shnayim yotzi
v'yiten ktubah*, which means two רגלים regalim. *regalim* already they have to
get divorced if that's the duration of the vow. אימא סיפא שלשה
יוציא Yotzi, *Eima seifa shelosha yotzi*, then the end says three he
has to divorce. to be things up to three, you have to
get the you have to get divorced. השנים יקיים, two you would
be able to manage. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, סיפא אתאן לכהנת. seifa
asan l'kohenet. Oh, the difference is a woman married to a כהן
kohen who we're always going to be a little bit more hesitant
because it'll be irreversible. So a woman not married to a כהן
kohen already by two רגלים it's going to get we'll say get
divorced, but woman married to a כהן kohen we'll give him three
רגלים. ורבי יהודה היא, V'Rabbi Yehuda hi, and it's רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda who makes a difference between married to a ישראל Yisrael and
married to a כהן. kohen. אמר רבא בר עולא לא קשיא, Amar
Rava bar Ulla lo kashya, he gives another distinction, כאן ברדופה כאן
שאינה רדופה. kan birdufa kan she'eina redufa. It depends about the woman.
Now remember this woman might be a whole ripe old age of
twelve and a half, you know, or you know, thirteen. Maybe she's
even a real old maid of fourteen or something. So she might
very much want to go not just to, you know, back to
her family home, maybe she's not really feeling ready for married life.
Then you also understand maybe why he's trying to prevent it. It's
not just we're not going to visit the in-laws, it's like maybe
he feels that she hasn't, you know, acculturated herself to living with
her husband and she still wants to be, you know, be living
in her family home. And if you think about how old the
girls were, you know, there's you can understand that. So if she's
somebody that is like constantly running there, then you know, then it's
obviously on the one hand you understand more why he might be
taking the vow, but you also understand why it's more oppressive, whereas
if it's somebody who, you know, will visit their parents every now
and then, it's less oppressive and it would have to be three
רגלים. Okay. אז הייתי בעיניו כמוצאת שלום, Az hiyasi be'enav kemotzes shalom,
quote from שיר השירים Shir HaShirim we just read it, פסח, Pesach,
then I was in his eyes like one who found favor found
peace. אמר רבי יוחנן ככלה שנמצאת שלמה בבית חמיה, Amar Rabbi Yochanan
kekallah shenimtzes shleimah b'veis chamia, it's a, it's one that finds favor
in her husband's house, ורדופה לילך להגיד שבחה בבית אביה, v'redufa leilech
lehagid shivchah b'veis aviha,
and then she goes and she tells her her family how how
wonderful things are in her new home. So actually having a, it's
not, you know, obviously there's a reason it's quoted here but whether
it's meant to illustrate, you know, the previous point or just a
nice little דרשה drasha about the reality about going back to your
father's house, but maybe what it's also trying to do is set
up the idea that you could have a כלה kallah who wants
to be with her parents not because things aren't working out or
she hasn't, you know, acculturated herself to living with her husband, but
she still feels no, maybe she's totally happy in her husband's house
but she still feels such a close connection to her parents that
she wants to go and spend time with them and talk to
them about how wonderful things are. Okay. והיה ביום ההוא נאם ה׳
תקראי אישי ולא תקראי לי עוד בעלי. V'haya bayom hahu neum Hashem
tikre'i ishi v'lo tikre'i li od ba'ali.
On that day you will call me your your man and you
will not call me your husband. Or now of course the point
here is is that the word it part the end of the
פסוק pasuk is והסירתי את שם הבעלים מפיך. vahasirosi es shem habalim
mipiha. I will remove the name of the בעלים, Be'alim, which were
the Canaanite gods, from your mouth. So actually it means that the
worship, the simple sense of the דרשה drasha is the worship of
me God will be free from any sort of association and idolatrous
types of things because you know בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael were always
slipping into idolatry, so it'll be a pure worship there won't even
be any echoes any hints of any of that idolatry. But of
course this פסוק pasuk is also might be saying something about the
nature of marriage. What does it mean to consider your husband, you
know, your man or your or your master? Right, בעל ba'al means
exactly, בעל ba'al has that whole sense of being master, it also
had sense of sex, right? בועליך עושיך, Bo'alaich osaich, right, so the
you know so it's very much about sort of of the of
the male dominance and mastery and how sex might be even be
an expression of that mastery, you know it's a very different relationship.
איש Ish and אשה Isha are very much equal, man and woman,
right, you know like if you think about how they used to
sort of say, you know, I now pronounce you man and wife,
right, not husband and wife, right, not man and woman, man and
wife. The man is like, you know, his status hasn't changed, he's
always the man, now she's my wife. Okay, so saying that it's
איש Ish and אשה Isha as opposed to, you know, I don't
know, איש ובעלה, ish v'ba'alah, אשה ובעלה isha v'ba'alah is a very
different way of thinking about the relationship. So this is as you
can imagine this is a פסוק pasuk that, you know,
contemporary feminists or people with more contemporary sensibilities, you know, really like
in terms of expressing different ways of, you know, of expressing what
the how to think of a marriage and that this is really
putting out that the איש Ish and אשה is, you know, is
the right way. So anyway, so let's see what the גמרא Gemara
does with it. אמר רבי יוחנן ככלה בבית חמיה ולא ככלה בבית
אביה. Amar Rabbi Yochanan kekallah b'veis chamia v'lo kekallah b'veis aviha. It
means that he says basically that you'll be somebody who's happy in
her father-in-law's house, father-in-law's house really means her husband's house, right, and
is not the constantly going back to her father's house. So she's
at peace with being with her husband. What exactly that has to
do with אישי ולא תקראי לי עוד בעלי Ishi v'lo tikre'i li
od Ba'ali I can't really tell you. רש״י Rashi says לשון אישות
ונישואין lashon ishuss v'nisu'in
and רש״י Rashi ככלה בבית חמיה שכבר ניסת וגסה לבה בבעלה ואינה
בושה הימנו. kekallah b'veis chamia shekevar nises vegassa libah b'ba'alah ve'einah boshah
himenu. So רש״י Rashi just I think suggests that the idea of
איש Ish and אשה is more that sort of sense like you
have in בראשית Bereishis על כן יעזב איש את אביו ואת אמו
ודבק באשתו, Al kein ya'azov ish es aviv v'es imo v'davak b'ishto,
right, so איש Ish and אשה has a sense of coming together
and being one unit as opposed to a בעל, ba'al, yes, maybe
it has sex. mastery, but it’s not the same idea of being
one unit, so she still feels connected to her father’s house. Okay.
המדיר אשתו. Hamadir ishto. I have a good joke about this but
we're a little behind. I'll just give you the punchline. You're going
to lose with the punchline, but anyway, about this idea of running
back to the father's house on רגל אחד. The short version is,
you know, the guy calls mom, how's everything going? It's okay, but
your father and I, we're getting a divorce. What? You're getting a
divorce? You've had 50 years, you have three kids, ten grandkids. It's
enough, we're just, we're getting a divorce. He goes back and forth.
Listen, Mom, פסח Pesach is coming up, two weeks. Don't do anything.
Don't rush into anything, you know. I'll come with Rachel and the
kids, we'll sit, we'll talk about it, just, you know, just hold
on, okay? So alright, fine, whatever. Hangs up the phone, turns to
her husband says, told you I could get the kids to come
for פסח. Pesach. So the point was how I
got them to come for פסח Pesach but I don't know what
we're going to do for ראש
השנה.
Rosh Hashanah.
Alright, anyway. Alright.
And now the ברייתא braita says like this.
Okay. בשלמא Bishlama now, המדיר אשתו מבית המשתה. Hamadir ishto mibeit hamishteh.
She can't go to wedding parties or to or to a שבעה
shiva house. בשלמא לבית המשתה איכא נעול בפניה. Bishlama lebeit hamishteh ika
neul befaneha.
So I get the idea that going to a wedding party, you're
lacking the door in her presence, you're not allowing her to have
certain pleasures and enjoyments. אלא לבית האבל, Ela lebeit ha'avel, but of
a house of mourning, מאי נעול בפניה איכא, mai neul befaneha ika,
what type of locking the door is there? So תנא, tana, so
we learned in a ברייתא, braita, למחר היא מתה ואין כל בריה
סופדתה. lemachar hi meitah ve-ein kol beryah sofadtah. No, there is an
issue because in the future she'll, she'll die
and other people won't come and eulogize her. She never showed up
to anybody else's funerals. So, you know, and she'll so yeah, it
impacts somebody if they're not able to be there for other people.
You know, you could say it's not only going to impact her
when she dies, it'll impact her when she's alive. People will say,
you know, you didn't come to the funerals or whatever. That's a
very important part of communal and social life. And there are a
real loss about doing that. ואיכא דאמרי, Ve-ika de'amri, some say, ואין
כל בריה סופדנה, ve-ein kol beryah sofdenah, people won't even want to
bury her.
תניא, Tanya, we learned in a ברייתא, braita, רבי מאיר אומר, Rabbi
Meir omer, מאי דכתיב, mai de-chtiv, what's meant, טוב ללכת אל בית
האבל מללכת אל בית המשתה באשר הוא סוף כל האדם והחי יתן
אל לבו, tov lalechet el beit ha'avel milalechet el beit hamishteh ba'asher
hu sof kol ha'adam ve-hachai yitein el libo, better to go to
a house of mourning than to go to a house of rejoicing,
a wedding party, because this is the end of all of all
of all humans, והחי יתן אל לבו, ve-hachai yitein el libo,
the living will put it to heart. מאי והחי יתן אל לבו,
Mai ve-hachai yitein el libo, what should you be sort of putting
to heart when you're there at the place of mourning? דברים של
מיתה, Devarim shel mitah, things that relate to death. דספד יספדוניהו, Desapad
yesafdunihu,
if you somebody who eulogizes, people will eulogize him. דקבר יקברוניהו, Dekavar
yikvrunihu, if you're involved in burying somebody, they'll be involved in burying
you. דאדלי ידלוניהו, De'adli yadlunihu, somebody who is who like wails at
a funeral, people will wail over his death. דלווי ילוונוהו, Delavay yalvunuhu,
somebody who does the, you know, the לויה levayah that accompanies the
the coffin out to the out to the cemetery. דטען יטענוניהו, Detaan
yiteanunihu, somebody who is a pallbearer, people will do it for him.
So this is sort of the simple sense here is sort of
saying like, so when you're there, you should put to your heart
and realize, you know, your obligation to do to do all of
this type of, you know, being present for people and acts of,
what's sometimes called acts of חסד, chesed, although I don't like the
sort of some of the connotations of that. But anyway, your responsibility
to others and there's a whole reciprocity in that way. Obviously, that's
necessary so that people will do it for you. That's like, I'll
make you a deal, I'll come to my I'll come to your
funeral if you come to mine.
But anyway, but
more than that, more than just saying, so this is how we
have to be responsible when people are dying to the person who
died. You know, also the simple sense of the verse is החי
יתן אל לבו, hachai yitein el libo, like you have to realize,
hey, I'm going to be in that situation as well and that
obviously makes you take, you know, your whole life more seriously. Okay.
ואם היה טוען משום דבר אחר רשאי, but if he has a
some other thing that he's claiming as a legitimate reason, then it's
allowed. מאי דבר אחר, Mai davar acher, what's this other thing? אמר
רב יהודה אמר שמואל משום בני אדם פרוצים שמצויים שם, Amar Rav
Yehudah amar Shmuel mishum benei adam perutzim she-metzuyim sham, because he says
that there are, you know, very, um, what's the right word for
פרוצים? perutzim? Licentious, um, of low moral character. Promiscuous.
Promiscuous, that's better. Promiscuous people that are there. Um, and he doesn't
want her exposed to that. Doesn't necessarily mean he חושד choshed her
for having any particular, you know,
affiliation with them, but he doesn't like the gathering and thinks that
it's like, you know, you know, the crowd and what what and
what that could lead to. So אמר רב אשי לא אמרן אלא
דאיתחזק. Amar Rav Ashi lo amran ela de'itchazek. That's only if it's
been established that there are those types of people there and maybe,
you know, you wonder what the threshold is, right? אבל לא איתחזק
לא כל כמיניה, Aval lo itchazek lo kol kemineih, but if it
hasn't been established, he he's not believed. He doesn't have any ability
to make this claim, right? Which is good, you know, because he
could always make a claim and you could have a crazy jealous
husband. So there has to be some type of an objective standard.
But again, it is interesting. It's saying like, is this conceived as
intolerable that somebody should not do this? Well, in general it might
be intolerable. On the other hand, if it's basically is a very
a place of a promis you know, promiscuity or potential danger and
some people are doing drugs or, you know, whatever. Yeah well right
presumably it's more of a concern in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
then maybe it's not intolerable then certain types of people with certain
types of moral character do stay away. So you know it's interesting
in terms of the types of judgments חזל are making and the
you know חזל sort of
again I guess the question here is goes back to the תוספות
Tosafot of what does it mean יוציא. If יוציא means we really
force a divorce then we are getting very involved in people's marriages
to say this is sustainable this isn't. If יוציא more means we
advise a divorce and the real key issue is whether a כתובה
kesuvah, has to be paid or not you know and who's to
blame then that's a little bit less intrusive. You know this is
deserving of a divorce and if you know and we would push
it and then there would even be and then he'd have to
pay the כתובה kesubah, because he's to blame.
It could mean mixing at the חופה. chuppah.
Yeah I know even people have a different sense of what does
פרוצה Prutza mean. Okay ואם אמר לה מנשך תאמרי V'im amar lah
minshach tomri if he says make a vow that forces her to
say something that she shared to some with her husband to somebody
else or that he's shared to her to somebody else that's also
intolerable. What's intolerable about that? ותאמר Vetomar let her say it. אמר
רב יהודה Amar Rav Yehuda אמר שמואל amar Shmuel דברים של קלון
devarim shel kalon they are things they are shameful things. Okay they
are things that shouldn't be revealed. That would bring shame to him
presumably to the one who told it minimally. Okay או שתהא ממלאה
ומערה לאשפה
or she should fill up and spill out into the dunghill. So
what's that talking about? ותעביד V'saavid do this? Like what's the point?
What's it mean take out the garbage? אמר רב יהודה Amar Rav
Yehuda אמר שמואל amar Shmuel שתמלא ותנפץ. shetemaleh v'nofetzet.
So somehow the גמרא Gemara understands although this is also almost just
as euphemistic as the משנה Mishna the גמרא Gemara. somehow understood what
שמואל Shmuel means and what שמואל Shmuel is understood to be saying
is it means when she's filling up means when the husband when
they have sex and the husband you know
ejaculates and so her body is filled with semen and then she
washes it away. Okay so that's what she's doing. Fill up and
then spill it out. Okay the spilling of the seed outside the
body after they have yeah basically of so that she can't become
pregnant forcing her to wash out the semen.
ובמתניתא תנא U'vemasnisa tanya שתמלא עשרה כדי מים ותערה לאשפה. shetemaleh asara
kadei mayim v'saarah l'ashpah.
No just type of like nonsense work. Fill up ten buckets of
water and just spill it out into the garbage heap the dunghill.
So בשלמא B'shlama משום שמואל mishum Shmuel we understand שמואל Shmuel משום
הכי יוציא ויתן כתובה. mishum hachi yotzi v'yitein kesubah. He has to
divorce her because I mean even if a woman isn't obligated in
פרו ורבו pru u'rvu you know but to prevent the to prevent
her from becoming pregnant if she wants to become pregnant I mean
that's a whole discussion you know that we've seen but she has
a right to have kids even even if she's not obligated. Okay
so anyway and that's seen as a very...
And this is when she can become pregnant. I mean if she's
already old...
Yeah right presumably... Yeah right right yes. Okay so anyway so that's
seen as like you know just just like invasive and inappropriate and
and she might even have a right to have kids. Okay אלא
למתניתא Ella l'masnisa the one with the ברייתא braisa מאי נפקא למינה?
mai nafka l'mina? So let her do it. I mean not like
it's nice of the husband to make her do this stupid thing
but what's the big deal? I mean is that so terrible that
she has to that they have to get divorced? So ותעביד V'saavid
let her do it. אמר רבה בר בר חנה Amar Rabbah bar
bar Chana אמר רבי יוחנן amar Rabbi Yochanan מפני שנראית כשוטה mipnei
shenires k'shota because it makes her look like a crazy woman. Okay
so therefore yes it is even if like okay it's a stupid
hours of work big deal. No it's absurd. Why should I have
to do absurd things? Now נראית כשוטה nires k'shota right so נראית
כשוטה nires k'shota also has a public aspect but of course it
is worth mentioning you know in terms of realities of domestic abuse
that very often you know the type of ways in which sometimes
husbands I mean it's usually the husband you know husbands can be
so hyper controlling and you know make their wives do like everything
has to be perfect and has to do it all again and
whatever and often that leads to other forms of physical abuse people
that have that like you know hyper hyper control and very like
domineering in the home. So you know you could understand that it's
not just question of how it makes her appear in public. Okay
it's silly it's stupid but if he's having me do absurd things
and I always have to listen to him... You mean it's demeaning
and it's deeply problematic in terms of the marriage if he can
make me do these absurd things just because he wants them to
be done.
You mean the גמרא Gemara though is focusing on a public aspect?
Yeah I'm saying I know that that's not exactly what the גמרא
Gemara, is saying. נראית Nires has more to do with the public
aspect.
And it might be similar to והוחזק V'huchzak as far as by
the שדה sadeh that we haven't even know right that there's something
that's part of his character? Yeah that the he is particular about
you know going to weddings with mixed seating or whatever. Uh-huh but
if it's just
if he's not but he wants her to do this it's a
controlling thing.
Uh-huh maybe. I mean the והוחזק v'huchzak before wasn't והוחזק v'huchzak but
his character. והוחזק V'huchzak it was established that that was an actual
problem.
And this is a bad neighborhood but...
You could you could read it that way.
I don't think so. I think it means there's
local
community that you mean you don't believe him right?
Right, we don't believe him to say that there are that there
just because he's claiming there are people בני אדם פרוצים, bnei adam
prutzim, we don't believe him to say it unless it's been established
as a fact. Okay. So, alright, so the גמרא Gemara says, אמר
רב כהנא, Amar Rav Kahana, המדיר אשתו שלא תשאל ושלא תשאיל, hamadir
ishto shelo tishal v'shelo tash'il, a woman who makes a vow that
would that would that would have the impact of preventing his wife,
or תוספות Tosafot actually says that here actually a direct vow might
work, anyway, that she can't borrow certain vessels because המדיר says the
הנאה hana'ah of certain vessels are forbidden to me. So she can't
borrow it, because if she's borrowing it and using it in the
home, he's getting benefit from it. Or she can't lend out certain
vessels. So what types of vessels? נפה וכברה וריחים ותנור, nafa v'kivra
v'reikayim v'tanur, a sieve and a different type of a sieve and
a and a millstone and an oven. יוציא, all of these are
things that are I guess somewhat portable. יוציא ויתן כתובה, he has
to divorce her. Why? Even if he said she can't lend things?
משום שמשיא שם רע בשכנותיה, mishum she-mashi shem ra bi-shcheinosha, yeah, because
it gives her a bad reputation among her neighbors. This woman, she
won't even lend me a cup of flour, right? She won't even,
you know, so yeah, that really impacts the person's standing in the
community. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, it's been taught similarly, המדיר
אשתו שלא תשאיל ושלא תשאל, hamadir ishto shelo tash'il v'shelo tishal, even
to prevent her from borrowing makes gives her a bad reputation. Who
is this woman? She never asks us for a cup of flour,
she never comes, she never whatever. So even you say not borrowing,
you're just not imposing on people. No, אדרבה, aderaba, by borrowing actually
it's part of being community. So similarly, יוציא ויתן כתובה משום שמשיא
שם רע בשכנותיה. yotzi v'yitein kesuva mishum she-mashi shem ra bi-shcheinosha. וכן
היא, V'chen hi, that's exactly what oh that yeah, that's exactly, that
happens. A ברייתא braita sometimes is word for word. I've mentioned that
before. I mentioned that before, there's a whole phenomenon of Babylonian ברייתות.
braitos. וכן היא שנדרה שלא תשאל ושלא תשאיל, v'chen hi she-nadra shelo
tishal v'shelo tash'il, let's say she vowed that would prevent her from
borrowing or from lending, נפה וכברה וריחים ותנור, nafa v'kivra v'reikayim v'tanur,
ושלא תארוג בגדים נאים לבניה, v'shelo ta'arog begadim na'im l'vaneha, or
she actually took a vow that she's that she's not going to
be able to weave some nice clothes for her for her
for his kids,
which might
not which
isn't her obligation in terms of her
technical domestic
obligations, but nevertheless,
תצא
שלא בכתובה,
teitzei
shelo b'chesuva, then she's to
blame,
so
she goes out without a
כתובה, מפני שמשיאתו שם רע בשכניו,
mipnei she-mashi'aso shem
ra bi-shcheinav, it
makes him look bad. Your wife never never comes and borrows things,
your wife never lends us things. How come your kids don't have
nice new clothes for the יום טוב? Yom Tov? Right, so even
though it's his wife that's doing it, it also affects his standing
as well, you know, sort of like the אשת חיל, eishet chayil,
נודע בשערים בעלה, noda bashe'arim ba'ala, right? You know, his standing also
impacts about how his wife interacts with the neighbors. So this is
quite fascinating, right, about things that are not legally required or whatever
but have an impact in terms of one's social standing or communal
standing. And I would also say the interesting point about not borrowing
also has just as much implications about lending, like for example the
famous ברייתא braita that people know right about about what do you
call it? About דרכי שלום, darchei shalom, that we it says that
you know you give צדקה tzedakah to the עניים aniyim of the
non-Jews and you and you and you visit their sick and you
bury their dead מפני דרכי שלום. mipnei darchei shalom. What people often
forget is that the beginning of the ברייתא braita says that you
collect צדקה tzedakah from the non-Jews, right? You actually go to them
and and they have them contribute to the צדקה tzedakah מפני דרכי
שלום. mipnei darchei shalom. So how is it דרכי שלום darchei shalom
asking them for צדקה? tzedakah? But it is, because it's basically saying,
you know, you're part of the community and the relationship, if you're
not just an object of my charity, you know, we're connected, so
we we care for one another, we give to you know we
give to one another's צדקה tzedakah causes, yes.
So all of these all of these examples are examples of המדיר
את אשתו. hamadir es ishto. Right, so יוציא ויתן כתובה
because he's to blame.
Why the last?
Because she took the vow and it makes him look bad.
וכן היא שנדרה. v'chen hi she-nadra. First had him doing it and
then it had her doing it.
Oh, I'm sorry, I missed that.
Yeah. Okay, so now we've got a whole series of things that
create problems because of vows, and the vows are creating obstacles for
certain things being performed, and without the ability for those things to
be taken place, the marriage isn't seen as tenable and the question
is who's to blame. We now shift to not no issue about
vows, no like formal obstacle, but a reality of certain behaviors that
actually make the marriage continue to be not tenable or that need
to get divorced. Yes, Charlie. Okay, so let's take a look now
and now we get to this very highly relevant next
משנה. Mishna. ואלו יוצאות שלא בכתובה. V'eilu yotzos shelo b'chesuva. The following
are are are leave a marriage without a כתובה. Now of course
the question is leave, again, gets the question of do we force
a divorce, do we encourage a divorce? Okay, so we will talk
about that later. But but but the emphasis here is שלא בכתובה
shelo b'chesuva and certainly the sense is deserving of divorce, whether or
not to whatever degree the בית דין beis din gets involved. ולומדת?
u-lomedet?
So without a כתובה, העוברת על דת משה ויהודית. ha'overes al das
Moshe v'Yehudis. So it focus immediately focuses on יוצאות, yotzos, notice the
feminine, right, that the woman, I mean obviously it's the woman because
it's the גירושין geirushin is the woman leaving the house, but as
soon as... So it's about her behavior. She is actually acting in
a way that makes her at fault and therefore there's a divorce
without a כתובה, so A is saying that the marriage isn't really
tenable here and B she's to blame. So now we're going to
focus on what she's doing wrong. Okay, so she is transgressing the
Law of Moshe or the religion of Moshe and of the Jewish
women.
Law of Moshe means biblical laws and Jewish women means practices amongst
Jewish women.
Now what does that mean? It means like if she does מלאכה
melacha on יום טוב Yom Tov then you divorce her? So the
משנה Mishna is very specific. Not any type of transgression. I mean
mostly that's between her and God, right? Let's say she goes into
the bathroom and smokes on שבת, Shabbos, right? So you can divorce
your wife? I mean okay nobody whatever it's a major transgression but
what does that have to do with the marriage? So let's take
a look at what the משנה Mishna says. ואלו היא דת משה.
Ve'elu hi Das Moshe. What would be an example of transgressing the
Law of Moshe? מאכילתו שאינו מעושר. Ma'achilasah she'eino me'usar.
Feeding him food that is not kosher that doesn't have תרומות ומעשרות
terumos u'ma'asros taken from it. ומשמשתו נדה. U'meshameshso niddah. Has sex with
him when she's a נדה. niddah. ולא קוצה לה חלה. V'lo kotzah
la'challah. Does not remove the חלה challah from the dough so also
the food is not kosher. Okay. ונודרת ואינה מקיימת. V'noderes v'eina mekayemes.
And makes vows and does not satisfy them. So there's vows again.
But until that last one and the גמרא Gemara will explain that
last one it's all very clear. It's a type of transgression that
actually impacts him. Okay. In the first three cases actually it makes
him transgress דאורייתא. d'Oraisa. What the last one does we'll see. Okay
but it's actually a type of a thing that actually impacts him
and impacts you know and makes the marriage untenable. ואיזו היא דת
יהודית? Ve'eizo hi Das Yehudit? What is that יהודית? Yehudit?
יוצאה וראשה פרוע. Yotzah v'roshah parua. Goes out into the marketplace or
whatever outdoors and her head is uncovered. וטווה בשוק. V'tovah bashuk. And
she knits in the marketplace publicly, right? ומדברת עם כל אדם. U'medaberes
im kol adam. And she speaks with everybody. Okay so she's very
you know she just speaks with strange men. Okay now all of
these are the A or B or C. It's not that you
have to do all of these. Now obviously before we get to
the question of what is a woman's obligation to cover her hair
is it biblical or not that's not the interest of the משנה.
Mishna The משנה Mishna basically assumes it's not really an obligation it's
not a transgression but it's certain norms of modesty and norms of
behavior and presumably the problem here is not just that she's sinning
oh she's acting immodestly but when a man's wife is acting in
ways that are seen as immodest and sending certain signals to other
people or maybe intentionally or unintentionally inviting certain intention from you know
from strange men then or not so strange men whatever then that
is seen as compromising their relationship right? Because you know it's like
inviting potentially dangerous interactions or certainly a type of an uncomfortable energy
into the relationship. So that's why it's seen as problematic. One minute
let's just finish the משנה Mishna and then I'll take the question.
אבא שאול אומר אף המקללת יולדיו בפניו. Abba Shaul omer af hamekalelet
yoldav befanav. Even if a woman curses her husband's parents in her
husband's presence. So that's having nothing to do with like the issue
about other men but it's just like an inappropriate type of a
behavior
that's not tolerable that somebody should you know that somebody should have
his parents criticized by his spouse or her spouse but we're talking
about her doing the thing. Okay. רבי טרפון אומר אף הקולנית. Rabbi
Tarfon omer af hakolanit. Even somebody who is noisy right? We'll see
what that means in the
גמרא. Gemara ואיזו היא קולנית לכשהיא מדברת בתוך ביתה ושכניה שומעין קולה.
Ve'eizo hi kolanit? Likshehi medaberes betoch beisah u'shecheneha shom'in kolah. She can
speak so loud that everybody hears them. So everybody's hearing all of
what should be their private conversations you know? So they're yelling at
each other and having one of their fights and the neighbors are
hearing. A they're hearing that they're fighting and B maybe they're hearing
things that she's saying when they're fighting which are very embarrassing to
him. Okay so that would be something which is seen as intolerable.
Charlie? Well the גמרא Gemara will get to the more euphemistically than
that. Yes Charlie.
In the first part of the משנה Mishnah. those sins that she
caused him to commit are not simple לאוין. lavin. Those are more
severe.
Right. Although some of them might yes that's you mean because they're
כרת kares and so on. Right. A lot of those are כרת.
kares. That's a good point. Presumably normal כשרות kashrus would also be
included but you're right. Maybe the point is that nobody would even
think that she would feed him חזיר chazir you know? Because even
if הלכתית halakhically טבל tevel is worse than חזיר chazir at like
a deep resonance level you know it's you know like that is
more taboo חזיר chazir would be more taboo. דב Dov did you
want to ask something?
Okay it's a strange example of
כשרות.
kashrus. So can he say some of this is about
people not taking תרומות ומעשרות. terumos u'ma'asros. Right that's also a good
point you know עם הארץ. Am ha'aretz. It was a more common
scenario of right. By the way though it might be a lot
of this might be דרבנן d'Rabbanan you know at the time of
the משנה Mishnah that was a whole question whether תרומות ומעשרות terumos
u'ma'asros were דרבנן d'Rabbanan or דאורייתא d'Oraisa but it puts it under
דת משה. Das Moshe. Yes.
So that's what we were asking like you know let's say like
you know they weren't particularly religious and he hasn't really cared about
this and suddenly he says.
אגרות משה Igros Moshe has a question about that about a court
case about a guy got married to a woman and she didn't
cover her hair and he knew she wasn't going to cover her
hair and then he decided he was going to be פרום. frum.
and wants his wife to cover her hair. Yeah, so that's interesting
questions about changing the rules of the game in the middle. So
okay, not directly, but we'll just note that that's been discussed.
Yeah, but the other thing is if we take the literal interpretation
of קול אשה, kol isha, you know, like the way we said,
oh like, you know, the neighbors can hear her screaming, can it
go the other way around?
Well, that's the question about all of it. And about him, he
comes back from the store and he says, "Here's the meat you
asked me to buy" and he actually went to the non-kosher store
because it was cheaper, right? So okay, so the גמרא, Gemara yes,
it's interesting that until now the earlier משניות, Mishnayos, by the way,
lest we said, "Oh, the גמרא Gemara always assumes the wife is
to blame," almost all the משניות Mishnayos we had until now, he
was to blame. It was יוציא ויתן כתובה. So we certainly acknowledge
that the husband can be to blame for bad things going on
in the marriage, okay, and for being the source of the problem.
So here we're switching to her, but in presumably it could be
a similar case with him, maybe the גמרא Gemara saw this as
more common, you know, that this type of a, that these were
the scenarios more commonly when she was the one who was the
sort of, you know, person to blame or the person who was
an initiator. Okay, so let's take a look. But yeah, presumably it
works both ways. מאכילתו שאינו מעושר, Machilato she'eino me'usar, feeding him that's
not, that doesn't have תרומות ומעשרות. Trumos u'Maisros. היכי דמי, Heichi dami,
what's the case? אי ידעי, Ei yadei, if he's aware that that's
what she's doing, נפרוש, nifrosh, so don't eat it. How can he
say, "Oh, it's intolerable"? Now the גמרא Gemara later will actually say
it could be intolerable, even if he knows it. A, he doesn't
always know when she's doing it and whatever to always have to
be on guard, okay, so the גמרא Gemara will get to that.
But right now, this is what the גמרא Gemara is saying. If
he knows, so don't eat it. What's the big deal? אי לא
ידע, Ei lo yada, and if he doesn't know, מנא ידע, mena
yada, then how do you ever wind up finding out? So I
mean, if he's trusting her, he's trusting her. גמרא Gemara, says, yeah,
there are ways he could trust her and still find out. לא
צריכא דאמרה ליה היכא דאמרה ליה פלוני כהן תיקן לי את הכרי,
Lo tzricha d'amrah leih heicha d'amrah leih ploni Kohen tiken li es
hakari,
this, you know, this person, this כהן Kohen came and took תרומות
ומעשרות Trumos u'Maisros and helped me out in doing it. Doesn't have
to actually be a כהן, Kohen, but anyway, ואזל ושאליה, v'azal v'shaleih,
and then he went and he asked him or just as a
convo, came up in casual
conversation, ואישתכח שיקרא, v'ishtakach shikra, and it turned out that she was
lying. So he trusted her, but then evidence surfaced that made it
clear that it didn't happen.
Okay. ומשמשתו נדה, Umshameshasu niddah, has sex with him when she's a
נדה. niddah. היכי דמי, Heichi dami, what's the case? אי ידעי בה,
Ei yadei bah, if he knows, נפרוש, nifrosh, then don't have sex
with her. אי לא ידע, Ei lo yada, and if he doesn't
know and he's relying on her, נסמוך עליה, nismoch aleiha, so rely
on her. How does he, what ever becomes evident otherwise? דאמר רב
חיננא בר כהנא, D'amar Rav Chinana bar Kahana, we know that a
man is allowed to rely on his wife for this. אמר שמואל
מנין לנדה שסופרת לעצמה, Amar Shmuel minayin l'niddah shesoferes l'atzmah, how do
you know a נדה niddah counts for herself? Meaning, so she can
herself determine whether she's had her seven days and whether she's טהורה
tehorah or טמאה. temeiah. שנאמר וספרה לה שבעת ימים, Shene'emar v'safras lah
shivas yamim, she counts for herself, לעצמה, l'atzmah, so she can totally
do it privately and then she goes to the מקוה mikva and
she's totally believed.
So if he believed her, he should believe her. How do you
know otherwise? לא צריכא דאמרה ליה, Lo tzricha d'amrah leih, she said
to him, "פלוני חכם טיהר לי את הדם, ploni chacham teihar li
es hadam, she said to him, 'No, I had a שאלה shaila
and I asked the rabbi, and he told me that it wasn't
blood, that you know, and that I'm not a נדה.'" niddah. ואזל
ושאליה, v'azal v'shaleih, and maybe even he saw the blood, he saw
the blood on the sheets in the morning, and she said, "I'll
ask the rabbi," she came back, "I said I asked the rabbi,
he said it was okay." ואזל ושאליה, v'azal v'shaleih, and then the
husband asked the rabbi, ואישתכח שיקרא, v'ishtakach shikra, and it turned out
that she was lying.
So that's similar to the other case. ואי בעית אימא, V'ei bayis
eima, if you want you could say, כדרב יהודה דאמר רב יהודה,
k'd'Rav Yehuda d'amar Rav Yehuda, or like what Rav Yehuda says, הוחזקה
נדה בשכינותיה, huchzeka niddah bishcheinosiha, if a woman, it's been established that
she's a נדה niddah through her neighbors. What does that mean? Because
they would wear different clothes when they were, when the women were
נדה niddah because, you know, they didn't have the same type of
ease with laundry that we have nowadays. So if a woman is,
and they didn't have tampons and other things, so if the woman
is a נדה, niddah, then her clothes are getting soiled. She would
have special clothes she would wear for a נדה niddah not to
soil her regular clothes. So a woman, her neighbors saw her wearing
her נדה niddah clothes, so it was established that she was a
נדה. niddah. I mean, they didn't have direct knowledge, but they had
indirect knowledge. בעלה לוקה משום נדה, Baalah lokei mishum niddah, and then
the husband is seen having sex with her that, you know, you
know, while the day before and the day after she's wearing her
נדה niddah clothes, then that's enough of a basis to give the
husband lashes, which is fascinating, like what type of evidence do you
need to establish the facts before you go ahead and give lashes,
don't you normally need עדים eidim and so on? But what's relevant
for us is the point that a woman could be determined to
be a נדה niddah based on the clothes that she's wearing. So
he trusted her that she wasn't a נדה, niddah, and then it
turns out that the neighbors reported that during the day when he
was away at work she was wearing her נדה niddah clothes. So
that would be another way where the evidence came to light. By
the way, because we're in the middle of ספירת העומר, Sefiras Ha'omer,
I can't resist looking at this little תוספות, Tosafos, וספרה לה לעצמה.
V'safras lah l'atzmah. תוספות Tosafos says,
ואם תאמר אמאי אינה מברכת זבה על ספירתה, V'im tomar amai einah
mivareches zavah al sefirashah, because actually the counting is not actually for
the נדה niddah in the תורה, Torah, the counting is actually for
a זבה zavah who counts seven clean days. And nowadays that women
also treat themselves as not only נדה niddah but also זבה zavah
and have seven clean days, so תוספות Tosafos says why not make
a ברכה? bracha? Right? We make a ברכה bracha on ספירת העומר,
Sefiras Ha'omer, we make a ברכה bracha on זבה, zavah, why not
make a ברכה bracha אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו על ספירת זבה asher
kidishanu b'mitzvosav v'tzivanu al sefiras zavah or something? ויש לומר, V'yesh lomar,
כמו שמברכין על ספירת העומר דכתיב וספרתם לכם, k'mo shemivarchin al sefiras
ha'omer d'chsiv u'sfartem lachem, and same it says, you know,
וספרתם לכם. v'safartem lachem. ויש לומר דאין מברכין אלא ביובל שמברכין בית
דין בכל שנה v'yesh lomar d'ein mivarchin ela b'Yovel shemivarchin Beit Din
b'chol shana שלעולם יוכל למנות כסדר. she'l'olam yuchal limnot k'seder. וכן אומר,
v'chein omer, okay, that you're always going to sort of have the
full count. אבל זבה שאם ראתה סתרה אין לה למנות, aval zava
she'im ra'ata satra ein lah limnot, but a woman who's getting seven
days of not blood, if there's bleeding one day, she'll have to
start over again. So it will turn out that the first counting
wasn't a good counting, because she'll have to start again from the
beginning if she bleeds anytime during that period, which is interesting. Most,
it turns it into like this formal act of this מעשה ma'aseh
counting, you know, most פוסקים poskim assume that the real answer to
תוספות's Tosafot question is that there's not an act of counting, it's
just like recording, noting that it's, you know, how many days it's
been. But that's important in terms of the whole idea of בדיקת
שבעה נקיים bdikat shiva nekiyim and so on. Yes.
That seems to work by the idea that there's one מצוה mitzvah
to count for forty-nine days.
All right, I'm not going there right now. Okay, but you're right,
but it still might be separate מצות mitzvot but only if they're
whatever, yes. It's part of a larger continuity.
You can assume for תוספות Tosafot it's a מצות עשה שהזמן גרמא
mitzvat aseh she'hazman grama that women are פטור. patur.
Yeah, that seems to be how he's looking at it, that's true.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this,
ולא קוצה לה חלה, v'lo kotza lah challah, she's not taking חלה.
challah. היכי דמי? heichi dami? What's the case? אי ידעה נפרש, ei
yad'a nifrosh, if he knows let him not eat it. אי לא
ידעה מי ידע, ei lo yad'a mi yada, if he doesn't know
he doesn't know. לא צריכה דאמר לה פלוני גבל תיקן לי
את העיסה, lo tzricha d'amar lah ploni gaval tikein li et ha'isa,
so-and-so the kneader,
K-N-E-A-D-E-R, the kneader, you know, who I brought the dough to to
knead and he took חלה challah for me. ואזל ושייליה ואשתכח שקרא,
v'azal v'shayeileh v'ishtakach shikra, and he went and he asked him and
he found out that she was lying. Okay, it's interesting because he
went proactively and he asked him, so clearly he suspects her. ונודר
ואינו מקיים. v'nodeir v'eino mekayeim. Now the one that we didn't understand
was not fulfilling vows, what does that have to do with the
relationship? דאמר מר, d'amar mar,
because the master teaches, בעוון נדרים בנים מתים, ba'avon nedarim banim meitim,
for vows that are not fulfilled, the children die. שנאמר אל תתן
את פיך לחטיא את בשרך, shene'emar al titein et picha lachati et
b'sarecha, as it is said, don't give your mouth to cause a
sin upon your flesh. So if you don't fulfill what you say
with your mouth, it'll be your flesh and blood, your children that
will pay the cost. ואיזה הן מעשי ידיו? v'eizeh hen ma'aseh yadav?
And the end of the פסוק pasuk is וחבל את מעשה ידיך,
v'chibel et ma'asei yadecha,
the labor of your hands will be destroyed. ואיזה הן מעשי ידיו
של אדם הוי אומר בניו ובנותיו, v'eizeh hen ma'asei yadav shel adam
hevei omer banav u'vnotav, sons and daughters. רב נחמן אמר מהכא, Rav
Nachman amar meihacha, לשוא הכיתי את בניכם, lashav hickeiti et b'neichem, for
naught you have caused me to slay your children or to smite
your children. לשוא על עסקי שוא, lashav al iskei shav,
for things that are about שוא, shav, unfulfilled vows, right, like a
שבועת שוא. shvuat shav. Okay.
תניא. Tanya.
So anyway, what's this is obviously very troubling theology because we very
much, you know, there are, the תורה Torah on the one hand
has, you know, לא יומתו אבות על בנים ובנים לא יומתו על
אבות איש בחטאו יומתו. lo yumsu avos al banim u'vanim lo yumsu
al avos ish bechet'o yumasu. And then of course you have in
the עשרת הדברות, Aseret HaDibrot, right, פוקד עוון אבות על בנים ועל
שלשים ועל רבעים. poked avon avot al banim v'al shileishim v'al ribeium.
So we tend to bracket that idea of visiting the sins of
the fathers on the children, but that definitely is a theological idea
that is present, and, you know, particularly also from a time from
sort of an idea of thinking about children as one's property, right,
you know. So, I mean, just think about איוב, Iyov, right, God
tests איוב Iyov and he kills his kids and the children die
and then at the end of the story says, okay, so I'll
give you double back your children. You know, what?
But anyway, so, you know, if we, so this is obviously what
this is a part of. But anyway, now you see how it
impacts the marriage because of the, because of what's understood to be
the theological or the, you know, the consequences of not fulfilling vows.
תניא ונתנו ברייתא. Tanya v'tanu braisa. הכי רבי מאיר אומר, hachi Rabbi
Meir omer, כל היודע באשתו שנודרת ואינה מקיימת, kol hayodeia b'ishto shenoderet
v'eina mekayemet, if a man knows that his wife's taking vows and
not fulfilling them, יחזיר וידירנה. yachzir v'yadirna. So he should go and
he should make a vow on her. So the גמרא Gemara. says,
ידירנה במאי מתקן לה? yadirna b'mai matkein lah? How does that help
anything? אלא יחזיר ויקניטנה. ela yachzir v'yaknitena. No, get her angry כדי
שתדור בפניו. kdei shetidor b'fanav.
So if she's anyway going to take a vow, make sure that
you're around when she's taking a vow. How do you make sure
that you're around when she's taking a vow? Get her angry when
therefore she'll take the vow, ויפר לה, v'yafer lah, and then you'll
be able to annul it. Of course the problem is fine, that's
the vow that she makes in your presence because you got her
angry. What about the vow she's making not in your presence? That
doesn't necessarily, somehow that doesn't, I don't understand how that gets all
of her vows to always be the ones made in the presence.
Every day, whatever נדרים nedarim you have are מופר.
mufar. So תוספות Tosafot discusses that. But then between the time she
made it and between the time you were מפר, mefer, maybe she
transgressed. And also there's a question whether the husband has to hear.
That's like the other joke, right, about the guy who's the actuary
who was like afraid to go onto, you know, on planes because
he figured out the odds
because he knew
I heard the, because he figured out the odds of there being
a bomb on a plane so he was, and if he had
to go he was always like a bundle of nerves and then
one day he was on a flight with his friend and he
was completely calm. He says, I don't understand, what happened? How come
you're so calm? He says, ah, he says, this time I brought
a bomb on the plane, think about the odds of there being
two bombs. So
just because you make her take a vow in front of you,
what does that do to her making a vow not in front
of you? I don't know. Anyway.
Can she take a נדר neder completely in private? Does it always
have to be in
the presence...
Yes. No. No. Totally. Yeah. So if he's מפר mefer it at
the end of the day, it doesn't work retroactively from the time
that it's been
made.
No.
Right, well, that's a good point.
Let's get it out in the open. That's true. Okay. Okay, so
anyway, so now אמרו לו, amru lo, they said back to רבי
מאיר, Rebbi Meir, and this gets back to probably a better answer
to the earlier גמרות, Gemaros, אמרו לו, amru lo, אין אדם דר
עם נחש בכפיפה. ein adam dar im nachash b'chfifah.
A person can't be made to live with a snake in the
same like in the same basket. So, you know, somebody that you
always have to be on guard of, that might bite you, and
that the danger and say, oh, well, protect yourself. You know, the
fact that, okay, I can try to make sure that I'm always
there to annul the vows, that's like that's not a tenable situation.
And that could be the same answer about the כשרות, kashrus, you
know, don't tell me just don't eat it. I can't be... it's
not a tenable situation.
They said this to רבי מאיר. Rebbi Meir. Okay, so because you're
saying don't... that's not going to solve the problem. He says, oh,
you don't have to get divorced, just make her take the vows
in front of you. No, that's not tenable.
Well, that's also true. Yeah, absolutely, if you don't trust, right, exactly.
תניא, tanya, yeah, but that's a really good point. Like it's not
just the transgression, it's what is this doing in terms of the
whole marital trust? Absolutely. תניא, tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, beraita,
רבי יהודה אומר, Rebbi Yehuda omer, כל יודע באשתו שאינה קוצה לו
חלה, kol yodeia b'ishto she'eina kotza lo challah,
רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda says like the גמרא Gemara said before, if
you know your wife isn't taking חלה, challah, יחזור ויפריש אחריה, yachazor
v'yafrish achareha, so take... so be מפריש mafrish it again.
אמרו לו, amru lo,
אין אדם דר עם נחש בכפיפה. ein adam dar im nachash b'chfifah.
No, that's not tenable. So that's the answer. You might know, but
it's still not reasonable to say that you have to always be
on guard and have to always be, you know, go and double
checking and whatever. Okay. מאן דמתני להא, man d'masni l'ha, כל שכן
הא. kol shekein ha. If you say that that is true about
the case of the what do you call it,
about the חלה, challah, that you can't... that it's intolerable, certainly the
case of vows is... I'm sorry, no. If you think that
the case of חלה challah is solvable, that you can be, you
know, then you could... then you would certainly say the case of
the vows is solvable. אבל מאן דמתני הכא, aval man d'masni hacha,
but if the case... if you're only saying that the vows you
can tolerate, אבל הכא, aval hacha, חלה challah would be intolerable. זימני
דמיקרי ואכלי, zimni d'mikri v'achli,
because every single day you're eating food. So to say every now
and then you have to be on your guard about vows is
one thing; to say every single day you have to be on
your guard about food is a very different thing. Now this idea
of אין אדם דר בכפיפה עם נחש, ein adam dar b'chfifah im
nachash, to get back to an earlier גמרא Gemara and also something
very relevant to the עגונה agunah situation, is what the רמב"ם Rambam
says with... in terms of a woman who says that she finds
her husband, you know, repugnant and cannot have sex with her husband.
And remember we discussed before that the רמב"ם Rambam would say that
if a woman makes that claim, you force the husband to give
a גט, get, even though he doesn't pay a כתובה, because she's
the one that's making the claim, but... but you force him to
give a גט. get. And the רמב"ם Rambam justifies it by saying
אין אדם דר בכפיפה עם נחש, ein adam dar b'chfifah im nachash,
right, so from the woman's perspective. You can't force somebody to live
with a snake. So there, it's not making somebody transgress, but to
live with somebody that she finds repugnant to her is also a
type of living with a snake and also somebody who'd be expecting
to have sex and, you know, and that... and that would be
intolerable for you. Okay, ואיזוהי דת יהודית? v'eizuhi das yehudit? Now we
get to covering the hair. What is דת יהודית? das yehudit? יוצאה
וראשה פרוע, yotzah v'roshah parua, going out with a hair uncovered. ראשה
פרוע, roshah parua, says the גמרא, Gemara. hair uncovered, דאורייתא... d'oraisa... I
should actually... I think I've been saying hair, but I need to
be more accurate because it's head, head uncovered. Because I'll just say
one sentence about this, obviously this is a whole שיעור shiur in
itself. But this גמרא Gemara makes the idea of covered head and
uncovered head an issue about married women and norms for married women
and in particular, as I mentioned, about attracting the attention of other
men. Which... which mean unmarried women it's not an issue and also
then the question is well, what are the norms? Maybe it's a
covering of the head, not a covering of the hair. How much
of the hair has to be covered? Right? So, you know, and
maybe it's not even covering. פרוע parua could mean like the hair
is wild. Some פוסקים poskim say that if the hair is like
cut short or braided, that might be enough. It might be like
not having free-flowing hair. That's... so it's very much a specific question
of what is the norm of sort of... of dress for a
married woman that doesn't announce her availability to other men. Because actually
this is something that is true about... about many cultures, that... married
women covered their hair and unmarried don't, because you know, hair is
free-flowing and hair catches people's eyes. So it's basically a way of
catching the attention of men and saying, you know, for when you're
in the market for getting married. But when you're already married, you
don't want to be catching the attention of strange men, so you
control that free-flowing hair. Okay, so that's what the issue is here.
And that leads to saying, okay, in this case you have to...
you don't have to cover every hair, you only have to cover
in these certain circumstances, not others. And that's the issue of our
גמרא. Gemara It's about married women and this type of a norm.
This is very different than the approach in the גמרא Gemara in
ברכות Berachos that says שער באשה ערווה, sear b'ishah ervah, the hair
of a woman is ערווה, ervah, which is about the hair, not
the head, and seems to be about all women, not just married
women. And there's a whole question about which גמרא Gemara you sort
of give emphasis to. Okay, but we're going to focus on our
גמרא. Gemara. So it's about covered the head. So... Well, right, but
it's a, you know, within the... right, exactly. Like let's say you
have different community... Ashkenazi women this way, Sephardi women this way, this
subgroup this way, and you do by... how do you
determine? Some women... ראש פרועה דאורייתא היא. Rosha perua de-Oraita hi. So
the גמרא Gemara says what do you mean?
It's not just a
norm, it's a biblical issue. דכתיב ופרע ראש האשה de-chtiv u-phara rosh
ha-isha that by the סוטה Sotah it says that the כהן Kohen
uncovers her head. ותנא דבי רבי ישמעאל, ve-tana devei Rabbi Yishmael, we
learn
out of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael אזהרה לבנות ישראל שלא יצאו בפרוע
ראש דאורייתא. azhara li-vnot Yisrael she-lo yetzu be-phrua rosh de-Oraita.
From here we see a... בפרוע ראש, be-phrua rosh, period, excuse me.
From here we see a prohibition against Jewish women going out with
an uncovered head. Now what do you mean prohibition? It just says
that he uncovers her head. So two very important, so I want
to read רש"י. Rashi. רש"י Rashi says אזהרה מדבעינא להכא לנבלה מדה
כנגד מדה azhara mi-di-be'ina le-hacha le-navlah middah k'neged middah
since the סוטה Sotah is being sort of shamed or yeah whatever
disfigured measure for measure כמו שעשתה להתנאות על בועלה k'mo she-asta le-hitna'ot
al bo'alah
the same way she made her beautified herself for her for
her paramour—when's the last time you used the word paramour—מכלל דאסור. mi-klal
de-assur. So you can infer that it's forbidden. Now how do you
infer that it's forbidden? So then רש"י Rashi says אי נמי ee
nami says רש"י Rashi מדכתיב ופרע מכלל דההיא שעתא לאו פרועה הוא.
mi-di-chtiv u-phara mi-klal de-hahi sha'ata lav pruah hu.
What you can infer is that until that moment it was covered.
So you don't infer that it was forbidden, you infer that the
norm was that it was covered. שמע מינה אין דרך בנות ישראל
לצאת בפרוע ראש. shema mina ein derech b'not Yisrael latzeit be-phrua rosh.
It wasn't the norm for them. וכן עיקר. ve-chein ikar.
So then it's funny, then it's not like
a biblical prohibition or obligation, it's just a norm that is recorded
in the תורה. Torah. And a number of ראשונים Rishonim and פוסקים
Poskim say this, they say אסמכתא מן התורה, asmachta min ha-Torah,
you know, or it's a norm in the תורה. Torah. There are
those that read it as a biblical prohibition, okay, but the גמרא
Gemara says that either way it's sourced in the תורה, Torah, so
it shouldn't be called דת יהודית. dat Yehudit. So the גמרא Gemara
says okay here's the difference. דאורייתא, de-Oraita, why is it called דת
יהודית? dat Yehudit? It's דת משה. dat Moshe. It's just a question
of which category the משנה Mishnah. put it in. It's sourced in
the תורה. Torah. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. דאורייתא de-Oraita
biblically קלתה שפיר דמי. kalta shapir dami.
A simple head covering, a basket, would be sufficient. דת יהודית, dat
Yehudit, but the דת יהודית dat Yehudit demands more. אפילו קלתה נמי
אסור. afilu kalta nami assur. That's not sufficient, you need more. So
what's the more? Is it how much of the head is covered?
Whether it's see-through or not see-through? Whether it's a basket or whatever?
It's not exactly clear what the differences are. But somehow דת משה
dat Moshe the norm in the תורה Torah demands a certain level,
דת יהודית dat Yehudit another level. And now we have a very
important גמרא. Gemara אמר רבי אסי אמר רבי יוחנן קלתה, Amar Rabbi
Assi amar Rabbi Yochanan kalta, this basket which is a minimal covering,
אין בה משום פרוע ראש. ein ba mishum prua rosh. That's sufficient,
you satisfy the obligations of covering the head. הוי בה רבי זירא,
Havei ba Rabbi Zeira, רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira asked on this, היכי?
heichi? What's היכא? heicha? Where are we talking about? אילימא בשוק, ilima
ba-shuk, if it's in the marketplace, דת יהודית היא. dat Yehudit hi.
We've just established that it might not be a biblical issue, but
דת יהודית dat Yehudit demands more of a covering, so the basket
is not sufficient. אלא בחצר. ela be-chatzer. So we're talking about in
her yard. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says אי אמרת הכי, ee
amrat hachi, if that means that in her yard she needs to
have it covered with a basket, right, if you're saying a basket
is good, so it needs to be covered in her yard. But
he says if that's true, לא הנחת בת לאברהם אבינו שיושבת תחת
בעלה. lo hinachta bat le-Avraham Avinu she-yoshevet tachat ba'alah. No women is
entitled to continue living with her husband. Meaning all of our women
are in their courtyards with their heads uncovered completely. So how can
you imply that there needs to be some cover in the yard?
In the yard women completely have their heads uncovered. And in the
marketplace it has to be more fully covered. So when is it
that this middle covering is needed but sufficient? So the גמרא Gemara
says אמר אביי ואיתימא רב כהנא מחצר לחצר דרך מבוי. amar Abaye
ve-itima Rav Kahana me-chatzer le-chatzer derech mavoi.
When it's needed and sufficient is when you're going from one yard
to the other by way of the by way of the alley.
Now I want to remind you what this looks like because this
is very important again. Remember that they had right all of their
houses with their חצירות chatzeirot opening up like here's the house right
and then this is the חצר chatzer right so they had their
houses with their yards right opening up into like into the well
this is the communal right this is their houses this is the
communal excuse me these are the houses this is a communal חצר
chatzer and then all of the חצירות chatzeirot right open up into
a מבוי mavoi into an alleyway. So if a woman is going
מחצר לחצר דרך מבוי me-chatzer le-chatzer derech mavoi
what she is doing is so this is like a court right
this is a shared חצר chatzer so she is going so first
of all it means that here she is in her court which
is court in her court where other houses open up to. My
point being it's not private. It's outdoors and it's in a communal
courtyard right and there she doesn't have to cover it at all.
But when she's running across the street to get to the other
courtyard her neighbor's court presumably and she's for a while crossing a
common a big common thoroughfare then she needs a minimal cover. So
what's significant about this is when she's actually spending time in the
מבוי mavoi or she's in the שוק shuk and she's in a
public space. What's important about this is is that the גמרא makes
it pretty clear that if a woman is not in a public
is in like a semi-private in this חצר chatzer it's not private.
the other houses open up into it, right? So it's not like
doesn't have to cover if she's in the privacy of her own
home and there are no other men around she can have her
head uncovered. There could be other men around. The question is how
much is considered a public space and how much is it considered
more of a private, not private that nobody else can be there,
but not a very public space. So a courtyard where just the
houses of the court open up into it and there are other
men around but it's not a public space, okay, that doesn't require
a covering. And that's again very important if you don't focus on
hair as ערווה erva and you focus on norms, then the emphasis
here is on public space. I should also say that the issue
about focusing on norms is what if the norms is that women
don't cover their head at all? Right, so if you say that
it's a norm in the תורה, Torah, does that mean that that
a norm that can change when the practice changes that even has
no covering? So that's an issue for contemporary discussion in פוסקים. poskim.
Let's try to just get quickly to the משנה. Mishnah התובה בשוק,
Ha-tova ba-shuk, she knits in the marketplace. רב יהודה אמר שמואל במראה
זרועותיה לבני אדם. Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel b'mar'eh zero'oteha livnei adam. What's
the problem of knitting in the marketplace? Because it exposes her arms
to people and therefore to men and they see her uncovered arms
and this
refers
to...
all right, exactly. You never hear of anybody talking about this as
the reason for getting divorced. רב חסדא אמר אבימי בתובה בורד כנגד
פניה. Rav Chisda amar Avimi bitova bevrad k'neged paneha. Now the problem
is that she's knitting and there's two ways of reading this. רש"י
Rashi reads it as ורד, vrad, the thread goes down in front
of her face, but face is a euphemism, goes like opposite her
genitals between her legs and that sort of also attracts suggestive or...
it's not that she's necessarily intending it but it gets people's attention
that's unwanted, at least unwanted by the husband if not by her.
תוספות Tosafot says that might be the word ורד כנגד פניה, vered
k'neged paneha, a rose, meaning that she has red string in front
of her face. Oh my god, red string turns people's attention and
they start looking at her face and reads face literally. Okay,
ומדברת עם כל אדם, um'daberet im kol adam, she'll speak to anybody.
רב יהודה אמר שמואל במשיחקת עם בחורים. Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel b'misacheket
im bachurim. So it doesn't just say... it doesn't just mean every
now and then have a conversation with a stranger. It means she's
kidding around with the young men, she's way too familiar, flirting. That's
a good word. אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן דזימנא
חדא הוה קאזלינא בתריה דרב עוקבא, Amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar
Rabbi Yochanan de-zimna chada hava kazlina batrei d'Rav Ukva,
once I was going following רב עוקבא. Rav Ukva. חזיתיה להאי ארביתא,
chazitei l'hai Arvayta,
I saw an Arab woman, דהוה יתבה וקשדיא פילכא, d'hava yasva ve-kashadya
pilcha,
she was sitting and she was throwing a... what's it called... the
knitting...
what's a פילכא pilcha called?
Spindle. Spindle, thank you. Throwing the spindle, ותובה ve-tova and she was...
and she was weaving, ורד כנגד פניה vrad k'neged paneha
and whatever, the string was going down in front of her, you
know, in front of her pubic area or it was the red
string in front of her face. כיון דחזיתינא Keivan de-chazitina and she
saw us,
פסקתיה לפילכא, paskatei l'pilcha, she severed
the spindle, she broke the string, שדיתיה shadyatei and she threw it,
like she intentionally threw it down in front of me, like you
know dropping the glove for the man to pick up. אמרה לי
עולם, Amra li ulam, young man, הב לי פילכא, hav li pelach,
give me back my spindle, okay, so she was obviously flirting with
him and accidentally dropping her thing so he would pick it up
and return it. אמר רב עוקבא, Amar Rav Ukva, so רב עוקבא
Rav Ukva said about her מילתא, milta, he said something regarding her,
he applied a case of a law of the משנה Mishnah to
her. So מאי מאי, mai mai, so what case did he apply
to her? So
מאי אמר בה mai amar bah? רבינא אמר תובה בשוק אמר בה.
Ravina amar tova ba-shuk amar bah. Oh, she's an example of this
woman who's knitting in the marketplace and getting attention of strange men.
רבנן
אמרי מדברת עם כל אדם אמר בה. Rabbanan amri m'daberet im kol
adam amar bah. No, this is the example of speaking with strange
men, not just the knitting. But again, it's not... it's interesting, it's
not משחקת עם בחורים misacheket im bachurim like with a lot, but
she's obviously seeking out flirtatious interactions, you know, and that's how he's
interpreting מדברת עם כל אדם, m'daberet im kol adam, specifically proactively trying
to have conversations with men and to have these flirtatious interactions.
So the פשט pshat in פרקי אבות, Pirkei Avot, אל תרבה שיחה
עם האשה al tarbeh sicha im ha-isha could mean "don't flirt".
Could be, right, although some of the applications in the גמרא aren't
that way. Let's get to the משנה. אבא שאול אומר אף המקללה
ילדיו בפניו.
Abba Shaul omer af ha-m'kalala
yeladav b'fanav. רב יהודה אמר שמואל במקללה ילדיו בפני מולידיו. Amar Rav
Yehuda amar Shmuel b'm'kalala yeladav bifnei molidav. So again, I don't exactly
get the grammar here, but basically it means cursing out not even
cursing out a man's parents in his presence but even cursing out
his presence in his son's presence. So grandparents. וסימנך אפרים ומנשה כראובן
ושמעון יהיו לי, V'simancha Efraim u-Menashe k'Reuven v'Shimon yihyu li, that grandsons
are like sons, so it's just as bad to curse out a
grandfather in the presence of the grandkids. אמר רבה דאמרה ליה, Amar
Rabbah de-amra lei, that she says to her kids, ניכליה אריה לסבא,
neichlei arya l'sabba, that a lion should eat your grandfather, באפי בראי
be-appei brai in the presence of her kids. So maybe she says
it to the husband but the kids are around or something, I
don't know. Okay, just to finish this up. רבי טרפון אומר אף
הקולנית, Rabbi Tarfon omer af ha-kolanit, the woman with the loud voice.
מאי קולנית Mai kolanit? אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל במשמעת קולה על
עסקי תשמיש. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel b'mashma'at kolah al iskei tashmish.
Okay, so that is... that her voice can be heard regarding matters
of sex.
במתניתא תנא, B'matnita tana, so meaning that she talks loudly and they
hear about... No, during sex, they can hear her voice. So רש"י
Rashi says it's because sex is painful to her
and she's yelling out during sex, very tragic description. You could just
say that, right, it's when she has, when she's having an orgasm,
she's very loud. Okay, but that's, anyway, that's obviously considered highly inappropriate,
or, you know, not tolerable in terms of the husband's sense of
privacy. ונתנייה גבי מומין במתניתין, venitniyah gabei mumin bematnitin, so the גמרא
says, ונתנייה גבי מומין במתניתין. venitniyah gabei mumin bematnitin. So why is
it, so according to the second thing, it should be listed in
the case of מומין, mumin, meaning our משנה talks about behavior that
can be controlled. If it's a problem about the woman screaming out,
then the גמרא understands that that's not behavior that can be controlled,
so it should be listed in the next, in another משנה that
deals with, sort of, intrinsic types of problems. So the גמרא says,
אלא מחוורתא כדשנין מעיקרא, ela mechvarta kedishanin me'ikara, the earlier answer is
better that she's talking too loudly, but it's not that her voice
is being heard during sex. Okay.